Register of the Dragiša Cvetković Papers, 1928-1965.
Hoover Institution Archives
Dragiša Cvetković Papers,
1928-1965.
70013
Cvetković, Dragisa, 1893-1969.
2 manuscript boxes (0.8 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
The collection consists of correspondence, reports, memoranda, and writings, relating to Yugoslav politics and foreign relations; the regency of Prince Paul from 1934 to 1941; the Cvetković-Maček agreement; Yugoslavia and the signing of the Tripartite Pact; the Našička Affair; the coup d'état of March 27, 1941; Yugoslavia during World War II; and Yugoslav émigré politics. Includes an unpublished history by D. Cvetković, entitled Rat ili Pakt: Unutarnja i Spoljna Politika Namesništva (1965). Also available on microfilm (2 reels).
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1970.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Alternate Forms Available
Also available on microfilm (2 reels).
Access Points
World War, 1939-1945.; World War, 1939-1945--Yugoslavia.; Yugoslavs in foreign countries.; Yugoslavia.; Yugoslavia--Foreign relations.; Yugoslavia--History--Coup d'etat, 1941.; Yugoslavia--Politics and government--1918-1945.; Statesmen--Yugoslavia.
Biographical Note.
1893 Born, Niš, Serbia
1923-1929 Mayor of Niš
1927 Elected as Representative to National Assembly
1928 Minister of Religion
1934-1935 Mayor of Niš
1935 Elected as Representative to National Assembly
1935 Minister of Social Policy and Health Minister of Justice
1938 Elected to National Assembly
1939 (February)- Served as Prime Minister of Yugoslavia 1941 (March 27)
1969 Died, Paris
Scope and Content of Collection
The collection consists of correspondence, reports, memoranda, and writings, relating to Yugoslav politics and foreign relations; the regency of Prince Paul from 1934 to 1941; the Cvetković-Maček agreement; Yugoslavia and the signing of the Tripartite Pact; the Našička Affair; the coup d'état of March 27, 1941; Yugoslavia during World War II; and Yugoslav émigré politics. Includes an unpublished history by D. Cvetković entitled Rat ili Pakt: Unutarnja i Spoljna Politika Namesništva (1965).
Container List
- Correspondence, 1944-1965. (Box 1.)
  Arranged alphabetically by name of correspondent.
  - Antić, Milan, 1962 (Folder 1: 1)
  - Bidault, Mrs. Georges, 1957 (Folder 1: 2)
  - Collège de l'Europe Libre, 1953 (Folder 1: 3)
  - Délégation à l'Assemblée Générale des Nations Unies Royaume de Belgique, 1951 (Folder 1: 4)
  - Dravoj, Josip, 1954 (Folder 1: 5)
  - Eden, Anthony, 1951 (Folder 1: 6)
  - Grom-Soldo, A., n.d. (Folder 1: 7)
  - Konjhodzich, Alija, 1961 (Folder 1: 8)
  - Kontić, Jovan, 1959-1964 (Folder 1: 9-10)
  - Kostić, Todor, 1950 (Folder 1: 11)
  - Kraus, Karl, circa 1950 (Folder 1: 12)
  - Krek, Miha, 1958-1965 (Folder 1: 13)
  - Kuzmanović, Ognjen, n.d. (Folder 1: 14)
  - Macek, Vladko, 1947-1963 (Folder 1: 15)
  - Mirković, Bora, 1948 (Folder 1: 16)
  - Peselj, Branko, 1947-1950 (Folder 1: 17)
  - Petrović, Dusan, 1963 (Folder 1: 18)
  - Pribicević, Adam, 1948-1957 (Folder 1: 19)
  - Roosevelt, Mrs. Franklin D. (Folder 1: 20)
  - Ruzić, Victor, 1959-1960 (Folder 1: 21)
  - Slijepcevic, Djoko, 1963 (Folder 1: 22)
  - Stanojevic, Aca, 1944 (Folder 1: 23)
  - Terrizzano, Jean, 1951 (Folder 1 :24)
  - United States, Department of State, 1952 (Folder 1: 25)
  - Vukcević, Radoje, 1960-1965 (Folder 1: 26)
  - Zalar, D., 1962 (Folder 1: 27)
  - Zivković, Dimitrije, 1952 (Folder 1: 28)
  - Unidentified (Folder 1: 29)
- Subject File, 1928-1963. (Box 1-2)
  Consists of reports, memoranda, correspondence, and printed material, arranged alphabetically by title or subject.
  - Albania, 1939 (Folder 1: 30)
  - Andjelinović, B. G., 1939 (Folder 1: 31)
  - Croatian Workers' Federation, 1960 (Folder 1: 32)
  - Cvetković-Maček Agreement, 1965 (Folder 1: 33)
  - Federation de Comites Nationaux d'Entr'aide des Serbes, des Croates, et des Slovenes en France, 1951-1953 (Folder 1: 34)
  - Franciscans in Croatia, 1941 (Folder 1: 35)
  - Gavrilo, Metropolitan of Montenegro and the Coast, 1937 (Folder 1: 36)
  - Maček, Vladko, 1937-1965 (Folder 1: 37)
  - Mihajlović, Ilija, 1938 (Folder 1: 38)
  - "Našička Affair," 1935 (Folder 1: 39)
  - Orientconstruct, American Oriental Construction Syndicate, 1928-1933 (Folder 1: 40-41)
  - Stanojević, Aca, 1935 (Folder 1: 42)
  - Stepinac, Alojz, 1942 (Folder 1: 43)
  - Stojadinavić, Milan, 1937 (Folder 1: 44)
  - Tripartite Pact, 1963 (Folder 2: 1)
  - World War II, Balkan Peninsula, 1963 (Folder 2: 2)
  - Yugoslav Medical Association, circa 1935 (Folder 2: 3)
  - Yugoslavia (Folder 2)
    - Census of 1931, occupational map, 1931 (Folder 2: 4)
    - Central Press Bureau, 1936-1937 (Folder 2: 5)
    - Coup of March 27, 1941 (Folder 2: 6)
    - Foreign Relations - Italy, circa 1937 (Folder 2: 7)
    - Ministry of the Army and Navy, circa 1937 (Folder 2: 8)
    - Ministry of Foreign Affairs, 1934-1938 (Folder 2: 9)
    - Office of His Majesty King Peter II, 1956 (Folder 2: 10)
    - Office of The Prince Regent, 1934-1939 (Folder 2: 11-12)
  - Yugoslavs in Germany, cirac 1937 (Folder 2: 13)
  - Zagreb, Office of the Police, 1929-1934 (Folder 2: 14-15)
- Writings, 1965. (Box No. 2.)
  - "Rat ili Pakt, Unutarnja i Spoljna Politika Namesnistva" (War or Treaty, Internal and Foreign Policy of the Regency), typewritten copy, Paris, 1965 (Folder 2: 16-20, Box 2)